Register of the Robert Harbold McDowell Papers, 1940-1969
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert Harbold McDowell Papers,
1940-1969
XX658
McDowell, Robert Harbold, b. 1894.
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Mihailovic, Draza, 1893-1946.; United States. Army.; World politics.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; World War, 1939-1945--Yugoslavia.; United States--Armed Forces.; Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavia--History--Axis occupation, 1941-1945.
Container List
- McDowell, Robert H. (Box 1)
  - The Key Strategic Role of the Serbs and Their Leader, General Mihailovich, in Southeast Europe During World War Two
  - Memoirs: Provisional Outline and Summary
  - Problems and Opportunities in U.S. Foreign Policy: Selected Intelligence Papers and Other Studies, 1940-1968
- An Evaluation of the Yugoslav Regime, undated (Box 2)
- The Role of Yugoslavia in the Second World War, undated
- A Statement by the Ann Arbor Committee for National Defense, R. H. McDowell one of the 14 signatories, undated
- McDowell, Robert H.
  - Summary of Background, undated
  - German Penetration in the Balkans, June 20, 1940. Includes related correspondence dated September 12, 1940 and September 21, 1940
  - A Statement of Belief, late 1940 or early 1941
- The Balkans and the Near East, (early?) 1941
- Rackym - The Developing Battlefront in the Caucasus and in Iran, November 23, 19
- McDowell, Robert H. - Report on Trip to Aleppo, 23 July to 6 August, 1943
- Copies of Paraphrased Cables, September 1943
- JICAME Report, Allies, Neutrals and Enemy Information, October 29, 1943
- McLean, F. H. R. - Report on Partisan Effort, Military Organization and Political Complexion, December 27, 1943
- St. Sava Conference in the Free Mountains of Yugoslavia, January 1944
- JICAME Reports
  - Yugoslavia--Alleged Conditions Among the Refugees at Bari, Italy, January 4, 1944
  - Yugoslavia--Alleged Hostile Views of Royalist Officer, January 29, 1944. Report prepared by Robert H. McDowell
  - Yugoslavia--Partisan Army Corps Commanders, January 29, 1944. Report prepared by Robert H. McDowell
  - Yugoslavia--The Croat Peasant Party and the Partisans, February 3, 1944
  - Yugoslavia--Alleged Data on Background of Tito, February 3, 1944
  - Yugoslavia--Nationalities in the Partisan Forces, February 3, 1944
  - Yugoslavia--Serb Orthodox Church and Partisan Movement, February 4, 1944
  - Yugoslavia--Character of Internal Dissension, February 8, 1944
  - Yugoslavia--Official Russian Statement on Treaty Overtures, February 9, 194
  - Yugoslavia--Croat-Serb Quisling Polemics, February 10, 1944
  - Yugoslavia--Internal Evidence of the Domestic Conflict, February 10, 1944
  - Yugoslavia--Conflict Between Partisans and Serbs, February 16, 1944
  - Yugoslavia--Estimate of Political and Diplomatic Situation, March 4, 1944. Report prepared by Robert H. McDowell
  - Yugoslavia--Defense of Serb Passivity, March 9, 1944
  - Yugoslavia--Bulgarian Estimate of Mihailovich Movement, March 15, 1944
  - Yugoslavia--Croat Estimate of Chetnik Movement, March 17, 1944. Report prepared by Robert H. McDowell
  - Croatia--Principal Puppet Gendarmerie Officers, March 29, 1944
- Observations on Partisan Forces by an Italian Artillery Officer Who Was Fighting With Tito's Forces Until April 1944, May 5, 1944
- Markham, R. H. - Best American Liaison Officer, May 8, 1944
- Correspondence
  - Harold E. Pride to T. E. Roderick, May 20, 1944 (1 letter); June 8, 1944, (2 letters)
  - K. W. Jones to D. S. Rice, May 23, 1944
- Extracts from PICME, The National Liberation Movement of Yugoslavia, April 1941-March 1944, June 1944
- McDowell, Robert H.
  - JICAME Report, Balkans--Some Notes on British Policy in Greece and Yugoslavia, June 5, 1944
  - Proposal for Establishment of U.S. Intelligence Mission with the Yugoslav Nationalist Forces in Serbia, June 6, 1944
  - JICAME Report, Yugoslavia--Sentiment Among Serbs and Chetnik Leaders, June 6, 1944
  - JICAME Report, Yugoslavia--Collaboration of Chetniks with Axis Forces, June 6, 1944
  - JICAME Report, Southeastern Europe--Allied Special Operations and Intelligence Organizations, June 10, 1944
  - JICAME Report, Yugoslavia--Appreciation of Present Partisan Situation and German Intentions, June 10, 1944
  - Estimate: Yugoslavia, the Partisans, June 16, 1944
  - JICAME Report, The Balkans--Intelligence Coverage by the British Force 133, June 17, 1944
- Markham, R. H. - Memorandum to W. Carroll on Situation in Slovenia, June 21, 1944
- McDowell, Robert H. - JICAME Report, Yugoslavia--Lack of Evidence to Support Partisan Claims, June 22, 1944
- Political Branch, MID, Political Estimate of Yugoslavia, June 26, 1944
- McDowell, Robert H. - JICAME Report, Yugoslavia--British Forces for Use in the Balkans, July 14, 1944
- JICAME Report, Yugoslavia--Proclamation by Partisan Wing of the Croat Peasant Party. Forwarding cover prepared by R. H. McDowell
- McDowell, Robert H.
  - JICAME Report, Yugoslavia--Letters Illustrating Conditions in Serbia, July 18, 1944
  - JICAME Report, Yugoslavia--Strength of the Partisan Army, July 21, 1944
- Disintegration of Yugoslav Partisan Organization, August 4, 1944. By McDowell or Markham
- Yugoslav Political Situation, September 12, 1944
- Alleged Use of American Arms and Equipment in Civil Strife Within Yugoslavia, September 22, 1944 (date of letter of transmittal; accompanying report dated September 7, 1944)
- McDowell, Robert H.
  - Memorandum for the Record: Conversations at Allied Headquarters, Caserta, Italy, November 1944
  - Report on the National Resistance Movement in Yugoslavia as Observed in Serbia and Bosnia in the Summer and Fall of 1944, November 22, 1944
- Milodragovich, John R. - Intelligence Report (covering 26 August-24 October 1944), November 22, 1944
- Rajacich, Michael - Field Reports from Serbia, November 22, 1944
- McDowell, Robert H. - JICAME Report, Yugoslavia--An Examination of Yugoslav Nationalism, November 27, 1944
- Mihailovich, Draja - Who Collaborated with the Germans? August 12, 1945 (Box 3)
- Report of Commission of Inquiry of the Committee for a Fair Trial for Draja Mihailovich, May 24, 1946
- The Significance to the United States of Developments in the Balkans Since the War, May 1947
- McDowell, Robert H.
  - Possible Shifts in the Strategic Situation in the Balkans, 1949
  - Evaluation of the Yugoslav Regime, September 28, 1950
- Holograph Notes from The Campaign of Truth, Operations Report as of December 31, 1951, State Department Document
- The Nature of the Treat; The Target Audience for our Doctrinal Warfare (2 paragraphs), 1952
- McDowell, Robert H.
  - Some Comments on U.S. Conduct of Foreign Policy, 1953
  - Problems of Soviet Communism: The Significance of the Beria Affair, July 1953
  - A Statement of Basic U.S. Objectives in Domestic and Foreign Affairs, February 12, 1954
  - The Role of Yugoslavia in European Affairs, February 23, 1954
  - U.S. Exploitation of Dissension in the Soviet Leadership, February 1955
  - Some Comments on Soviet Vulnerabilities and their Exploitation in "Cold War," 1957
  - A Concept for U.S. Unconventional Warfare Operations in a Situation of General War, April 29, 1957
  - A Concept for Unconventional Warfare Field Operations in the European Theater, August 20, 1957
  - A Concept for Unconventional Warfare Field Operations in the European Theater: A Study Prepared for the Chief of Special Warfare, 1958
  - The Introspective Mood of the Soviet Elite: Basis for Successful U.S. Foreign Policy: A Memorandum for the Record, 1958
  - Summary of Notes on U.S. Foreign Policy: The Soviet Union, March 18, 1958
  - What Is Wrong With American Foreign and Military Policy? 1960-1965
  - Russian Revolution and Civil War: A Grass Roots View, 1967
- Dimitrov, Georgi M.
  - Draza Michailovich, July 1968
  - Comments on Gen. Mikhailovich, July 1968